# Patrick Emami

74 Grandeville Rd SW Phone: +1 (904) 962 8293 Unit 1624 Email: pemami@nrel.gov

Rochester, MN 55902 Home: https://pemami4911.github.io

### **Research Statement**

I am a machine learning postdoctoral researcher working on neural representation learning, reinforcement learning, and AI for social good. My research has spanned topics including object-centric deep generative modeling, low-resource multi-object tracking, dynamic point cloud modeling, and traffic signal control. Mostly, I am curious about developing agents capable of learning challenging behaviors by reasoning about the world at the level of objects, like humans do.

## **Education**

| 2016–2021   | University of Florida, Gainesville, FL                           | Advisor: Dr. Sanjay Ranka |
|-------------|--|---------------------------|
|             | Ph.D., Computer Science (Machine Learning)                       |                           |
|             | Thesis: Neural algorithms for object-centric scene understanding |                           |
| Summer 2019 | University College London, London, UK                            | Marc Deisenroth &         |
|             | Machine Learning Summer School (MLSS)                            | Arthur Gretton            |
| 2012-2016   | University of Florida, Gainesville, FL                           |                           |
|             | B.Sc., Computer Engineering                                      | Cum Laude, GPA: 3.74/4.0  |

# **Research Experience**

#### National Renewable Energy Lab, Postdoctoral Researcher. January 2022–present

• Artificial Intelligence, Learning, and Intelligent Systems (ALIS) Lab.

Investigating constrained multi-agent reinforcement learning algorithms for energy-efficient building control and advancing our understanding of neural algorithms for large-scale black-box optimization.

### National Renewable Energy Lab, Research Intern. May 2021–August 2021

• *Complex Systems*, *Simulation*, *and Optimization Lab*. *Regional Mobility*. [Paper and code forthcoming] Developed a constrained deep reinforcement learning algorithm for NEMA-compliant traffic control using a "digital twin" of the Chattanooga, Tennessee road network.

#### MALT Lab, Graduate Research Assistant. 2016–2021

• EfficientMORL. ICML'21 [Github]

We present an interpretation of iterative assignment of pixels to object-centric slots as bottom-up inference in a hierarchical variational autoencoder. EfficientMORL has three key components: bottom-up inference with transformer-like attention to estimate a posterior distribution over slots, a top-down prior to regularize and disentangle the slots, and lightweight iterative posterior refinement to stabilize training. It is the first object-centric generative model to learn symmetric and disentangled representations while being reasonably efficient.

• Stochastic object-centric world models. NeurIPS '20 ORLR Workshop Spotlight. [Github]

Proposed a latent state space model based on variational autoencoders for jointly learning object-centric representations and dynamics for stochastic real-world video. Demonstrated superior segmentation and stochastic future prediction on a robotic manipulation benchmark data compared to prior work.

### UF Transportation Institute, Graduate Research Assistant. 2017–2021.

• MobileDR & Sensible. NSF Grant 1446813, T-ITS'21. [Open source release forthcoming]

Software engineering lead for Sensible, a distributed Python framework for real-time multi-sensor multi-object tracking at traffic intersections. Supports V2X communication and intersections with multiple roads each equipped with multiple sensors such as Econolite cameras and Smartmicro radars. Achieves GPU-less video tracking with a novel joint detection and re-identification deep convolutional network, MobileDR, running on PyTorch. Integrates with a real-time traffic signal optimizer for advanced adaptive signal control.

## **Publications**

#### **Peer-Reviewed Journals**

- [1] He, P., & **Emami, P.**, & Ranka, S., & Rangarajan, A. Learning Scene Dynamics From Point Cloud Sequences. IJCV Special Issue on 3D Vision. 2021.
- [2] **Emami, P.**, & Elefteriadou, L., & Ranka, S. Long-range Multi-Object Tracking at Traffic Intersections on Low-Power Devices. IEEE Transactions on Intelligent Transportation Systems. 2021. [UFTI article]
- [3] **Emami, P.**, & Pardalos, P. M., & Elefteriadou, L., & Ranka, S. Machine Learning Methods for Data Association in Multi-Object Tracking. ACM Computing Surveys, 53, 4, Article 69. 2020.
- [4] Pourmehrab, M., Emami, P., Martin-Gasulla, M., Wilson, J., Elefteriadou, L., Ranka, S. Signalized Intersection Performance with Automated and Conventional Vehicles: A Comparative Study. Journal of Transportation Engineering, Part A: Systems 146.9. 2020.

#### **Peer-Reviewed Conferences and Workshops**

- [1] He, P., **Emami, P.**, Ranka, S., Rangarajan, A. Self-Supervised Robust Scene Flow Estimation via the Alignment of Probability Density Functions. AAAI'22. **15% acceptance rate**.
- [2] **Emami, P.**, He, P., Ranka, S., Rangarajan, A. Efficient Iterative Amortized Inference for Learning Symmetric and Disentangled Multi-Object Representations. International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML'21). 2021. **21.5% acceptance rate**.
- [3] **Emami, P.**, He, P., Rangarajan, A., Ranka, S. A Symmetric and Object-Centric World Model for Stochastic Environments. 34th Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems Workshop on Object Representations for Learning and Reasoning (NeurIPS '20). 2020. **Spotlight**.
- [4] **Emami, P.\***, Vargas, L.\*, Traynor, P. On the Detection of Disinformation Campaign Activity with Network Analysis. CCSW 2020: The ACM Cloud Computing Security Workshop. 2020. \*Equal contribution
- [5] Emami, P., Pourmehrab, M., Martin-Gasulla, M., Ranka, S., Elefteriadou, L. A Comparison of Intelligent Signalized Intersection Controllers Under Mixed Traffic. IEEE Intelligent Transportation Systems Conference, 2018.
- [6] Omidvar, A., Pourmehrab, M., **Emami, P.**, Kiriazes, R., Esposito, J., Letter, C., Elefteriadou, L., Ranka, S., Crane, C. Deployment and Testing of Optimized Autonomous and Connected Vehicle Trajectories at a Closed-Course Signalized Intersection. Transportation Research Board's 97th, 2018.
- [7] **Emami, P.**, & Pourmehrab, M., & Elefteriadou, L., & Ranka, S., & Crane, C. A Demonstration of Fusing DSRC and Radar for Optimizing Intersection Performance. Automated Vehicles Symposium (AVS'17), 2017.
- [8] **Emami, P.**, Elefteriadou, L., Ranka, S. Tracking Vehicles Equipped with Dedicated Short-Range Communication at Traffic Intersections. 7th ACM International Symposium on Design and Analysis of Intelligent Vehicular Networks and Applications (DIVANet'17), 2017.
- [9] Hamlet, A., **Emami, P.**, Crane, C. The Cognitive Driving Framework: Joint Inference for Collision Prediction and Avoidance in Autonomous Vehicles. In the 15th International Conference on Control, Automation and Systems (ICCAS), pp. 1714-1719. IEEE, 2015.
- [10] Hamlet, A., **Emami, P.**, Crane, C. A Gesture Recognition System for Mobile Robots That Learns Online. In the 2014 IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS'14), pp. 2114-2119. IEEE, 2014.

## **Preprints**

- [1] **Emami, P.**, & Ranka, S. Learning Permutations with Sinkhorn Policy Gradient. arXiv:1805.07010 [cs.LG], 2018.
- [2] **Emami, P.**, & Panos M. P., & Elefteriadou, L., & Ranka, S. Machine Learning Methods for Solving Assignment Problems in Multi-Target Tracking. Under review at ACM Computing Surveys. arXiv:1802.06897 [cs.CV], 2018.

## **Blog Posts**

[1] **Emami, P**. Deep Deterministic Policy Gradients in Tensorflow. http://pemami4911.github.io/blog/2016/08/21/ddpg-rl.html. 2016. > 100K unique views (Google Analytics). [Github]

## **Professional Activities**

| 2022      | Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR), Reviewer                          |
|-----------|---|
| 2022      | International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR), Reviewer             |
| 2021      | Computer Vision and Image Understanding (CVIU), Reviewer                          |
| 2021      | International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCV), Reviewer                      |
| 2021      | Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS), Reviewer                         |
| 2021      | International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML), Reviewer                     |
| 2021      | IEEE Intelligent Transportation Systems Conference (ITSC), Reviewer               |
| 2021      | Transportation Research Record (TRR), Reviewer                                    |
| 2020      | NeurIPS Workshop on Interp. Inductive Biases and Phys., Reviewer                  |
| 2020      | Transportation Research Board Annual Meeting (TRBAM), Reviewer                    |
| 2020      | Optimization Letters, Reviewer  |
| 2019      | UF Informatics Institute Student Data Analysis Seminar, Co-Organizer              |
| 2018      | UF Informatics Institute Student Data Analysis Seminar, Co-Organizer              |
| 2018      | <b>International Conference on Machine Learning and Data Science</b> , Reviewer   |
| 2018      | <b>IEEE Intelligent Transportation Systems Conference</b> , Special Session Chair |
| 2018      | IEEE Intelligent Transportation Systems Conference (ITSC), Reviewer               |
| 2017      | <b>International Conference on Machine Learning and Data Science</b> , Reviewer   |
| 2017      | UF Informatics Institute Student Data Analysis Seminar, Co-Organizer              |
| 2016–2018 | UF Machine Learning Reading Group, Organizer                                      |

# **Professional Societies**

| 2018–present | Alpha Epsilon Lambda Graduate Honor Society, member |
|--------------|---|
| 2017–present | ACM, student member                                 |
| 2016–present | IEEE, student member                                |
| 2014–present | IEEE Eta Kappa Knu Honor Society, member            |

# **Selected Honors and Awards**

Top 10% Reviewer at ICML'21

2020 Student of the Year USDOT STRIDE Center (10 universities) (\$1,000)

2016–present McKnight Doctoral Fellowship (\$65,000)

2016–present CISE Department Graduate Research Fellowship (\$150,000)

2016 President's Honor Roll

2015–2016 Northrop Grumman Engineering Scholarship (\$1,000) 2014–2015 University Scholars Program Research Grant (\$1,750)

2014 IROS'14 Best Entertainment Robots and Systems Paper Finalist

# **Mentoring**

| Fall 2019–2021   | Yury Lebedev (Ph.D.)                                       | Univ. of Florida |
|------------------|--|------------------|
| Fall 2018–2021   | Kevin Chow (B.Sc., now Ph.D. at Tsinghua Univ.)            | Univ. of Florida |
| Fall-Summer 2018 | Anuran Rouchowdhury (M.Sc)                                 | Univ. of Florida |
| Summer 2018      | Ian Pelakh (B.Sc.)   | Univ. of Florida |
| Fall 2017        | Shalaka Naik (M.Sc), Individual Study                      | Univ. of Florida |
| Fall 2017        | Vivek Gade (M.Sc), Individual Study                        | Univ. of Florida |
| Summer 2017      | Jabari Wilson (SURF Fellow, now Ph.D. at Univ. of Florida) | Univ. of Alabama |

# **Teaching & Volunteering**

| 2021        | Junior Science, Engineering, and Humanities Symposium, Reviewer               |  |
|-------------|---|--|
|             | Reviewed 7 papers written by high school students for the speaker competition |  |
| Summer 2018 | Student Science Training Program, Instructor                                  |  |
|             | Designed & taught a 6-week short course on machine learning basics            |  |
| 2017–2018   | Teaching Youth Programming Essentials, Curriculum Lead                        |  |
|             | Responsible for designing and improving the UF TYPE programming curriculum    |  |
| 2016–2017   | Teaching Youth Programming Essentials, Instructor                             |  |
|             | Teach an after school Intro to Programming course at local high schools       |  |
| 2014–2015   | Association of Computer Engineers, Co-Founder and Project Manager             |  |
|             | Organized and presented at technical and professional development             |  |
|             | workshops for undergraduate computer engineering students                     |  |